<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-oauth-signed-http-request-02"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="HTTP Signed Messages">A Method for Signing HTTP Requests
    for OAuth</title>

    <author fullname="Justin Richer" initials="J." role="editor"
            surname="Richer">
      <address>
        <email>ietf@justin.richer.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="John Bradley" initials="J." surname="Bradley">
      <organization abbrev="Ping Identity">Ping Identity</organization>

      <address>
        <email>ve7jtb@ve7jtb.com</email>

        <uri>http://www.thread-safe.com/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Hannes Tschofenig" initials="H." surname="Tschofenig">
      <organization>ARM Limited</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city/>

          <code/>

          <country>Austria</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <email>Hannes.Tschofenig@gmx.net</email>

        <uri>http://www.tschofenig.priv.at</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="03" month="February" year="2016"/>

    <area>Security</area>

    <workgroup>OAuth Working Group</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document a method for offering data origin authentication and
      integrity protection of HTTP requests. To convey the relevant data items
      in the request a JSON-based encapsulation is used and the JSON Web
      Signature (JWS) technique is re-used. JWS offers integrity protection
      using symmetric as well as asymmetric cryptography.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>In order to prove possession of an access token and its associated
      key, an OAuth 2.0 client needs to compute some cryptographic function
      and present the results to the protected resource as a signature. The
      protected resource then needs to verify the signature and compare that
      to the expected keys associated with the access token. This is in
      addition to the normal token protections provided by a <xref
      target="RFC6750">bearer token</xref> and transport layer security
      (TLS).</t>

      <t>Furthermore, it is desirable to bind the signature to the HTTP
      request. Ideally, this should be done without replicating the
      information already present in the HTTP request more than required.
      However, many HTTP application frameworks insert extra headers, query
      parameters, and otherwise manipulate the HTTP request on its way from
      the web server into the application code itself. It is the goal of this
      draft to have a signature protection mechanism that is sufficiently
      robust against such deployment constraints while still providing
      sufficient security benefits.</t>

      <t>The key required for this signature calculation is distributed via
      mechanisms described in companion documents (see <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-oauth-pop-key-distribution"/> and <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-oauth-pop-architecture"/>). The JSON Web Signature
      (JWS) specification <xref target="RFC7515"/> is used for computing a
      digital signature (which uses asymmetric cryptography) or a keyed
      message digest (in case of symmetric cryptography).</t>

      <t>The mechanism described in this document assumes that a client is in
      possession of an access token and asociated key. That client then
      creates a JSON object including the access token, signs the JSON object
      using JWS, and issues an request to a resource server for access to a
      protected resource using the signed object as its authorization.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
      "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>

      <t>Other terms such as "client", "authorization server", "access token",
      and "protected resource" are inherited from <xref target="RFC6749">OAuth
      2.0</xref>.</t>

      <t>We use the term 'sign' (or 'signature') to denote both a keyed
      message digest and a digital signature operation.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Generating a JSON Object from an HTTP Request">
      <t>This specification uses JSON Web Signatures <xref target="RFC7515"/>
      to protect the access token and, optionally, parts of the request.</t>

      <t>This section describes how to generate a <xref
      target="RFC7159">JSON</xref> object from the HTTP request. Each value
      below is included as a member of the JSON object at the top level.</t>

      <t><list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="at">REQUIRED. The access token value. This string is
          assumed to have no particular format or structure and remains opaque
          to the client.</t>

          <t hangText="ts">RECOMMENDED. The timestamp. This integer provides
          replay protection of the signed JSON object. Its value MUST be a
          number containing an integer value representing number of whole
          integer seconds from midnight, January 1, 1970 GMT.</t>

          <t hangText="m">OPTIONAL. The HTTP Method used to make this request.
          This MUST be the uppercase HTTP verb as a JSON string.</t>

          <t hangText="u">OPTIONAL. The HTTP URL host component as a JSON
          string. This MAY include the port separated from the host by a colon
          in host:port format.</t>

          <t hangText="p">OPTIONAL. The HTTP URL path component of the request
          as an HTTP string.</t>

          <t hangText="q">OPTIONAL. The hashed HTTP URL query parameter map of
          the request as a two-part JSON array. The first part of this array
          is a JSON array listing all query parameters that were used in the
          calculation of the hash in the order that they were added to the
          hashed value as described below. The second part of this array is a
          JSON string containing the Base64URL encoded hash itself, calculated
          as described below.</t>

          <t hangText="h">OPTIONAL. The hashed HTTP request headers as a
          two-part JSON array. The first part of this array is a JSON array
          listing all headers that were used in the calculation of the hash in
          the order that they were added to the hashed value as described
          below. The second part of this array is a JSON string containing the
          Base64URL encoded hash itself, calculated as described below.</t>

          <t hangText="b">OPTIONAL. The base64URL encoded hash of the HTTP
          Request body, calculated as the SHA256 of the byte array of the
          body</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>All hashes SHALL be calculated using the SHA256 algorithm. [[ Note to
      WG: do we want crypto agility here? If so how do we signal this ]]</t>

      <t>The JSON object is signed using the algorithm appropriate to the
      associated access token key, usually communicated as part of <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-oauth-pop-key-distribution">key
      distribution</xref>.</t>

      <section title="Calculating the query parameter list and hash">
        <t>To generate the query parameter list and hash, the client creates
        two data objects: an ordered list of strings to hold the query
        parameter names and a string buffer to hold the data to be hashed.</t>

        <t>The client iterates through all query parameters in whatever order
        it chooses and for each query parameter it does the following:</t>

        <t><list style="numbers">
            <t>Adds the name of the query parameter to the end of the
            list.</t>

            <t>Encodes the name and value of the query parameter as
            "name=value" and appends it to the string buffer separated by the
            ampersand <spanx style="verb">&amp;</spanx> character.</t>
          </list>Repeated parameter names are processed separately with no
        special handling. Parameters MAY be skipped by the client if they are
        not required (or desired) to be covered by the signature.</t>

        <t>The client then calculates the hash over the resulting string
        buffer. The list and the hash result are added to a list as the value
        of the "q" member.</t>

        <t>For example, the query parameter set of "b=bar", "a=foo", "c=duck"
        is concatenated into the string:</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[b=bar&a=foo&c=duck]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>When added to the JSON structure using this process, the results
        are:</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA["q": [["b", "a", "c"], "u4LgkGUWhP9MsKrEjA4dizIllDXluDku6ZqCeyuR-JY"]]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="Calculating the header list and hash">
        <t>To generate the header list and hash, the client creates two data
        objects: an ordered list of strings to hold the header names and a
        string buffer to hold the data to be hashed.</t>

        <t>The client iterates through all query parameters in whatever order
        it chooses and for each query parameter it does the following:</t>

        <t><list style="numbers">
            <t>Lowercases the header name.</t>

            <t>Adds the name of the header to the end of the list.</t>

            <t>Encodes the name and value of the header as "name: value" and
            appends it to the string buffer separated by a newline <spanx
            style="verb">\n</spanx> character.</t>
          </list>Repeated header names are processed separately with no
        special handling. Headers MAY be skipped by the client if they are not
        required (or desired) to be covered by the signature.</t>

        <t>The client then calculates the hash over the resulting string
        buffer. The list and the hash result are added to a list as the value
        of the "h" member.</t>

        <t>For example, the headers "Content-Type: application/json" and
        "Etag: 742-3u8f34-3r2nvv3" are concatenated into the string:</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[content-type: application/json
etag: 742-3u8f34-3r2nvv3]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA["h": [["content-type", "etag"], "bZA981YJBrPlIzOvplbu3e7ueREXXr38vSkxIBYOaxI"]]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Sending the signed object">
      <t>In order to send the signed object to the protected resource, the
      client includes it in one of the following three places.</t>

      <section title="HTTP Authorization header">
        <t>The client SHOULD send the signed object to the protected resource
        in the Authorization header. The value of the signed object in JWS
        compact form is appended to the Authorization header as a PoP value.
        This is the preferred method. Note that if this method is used, the
        Authorization header MUST NOT be included in the protected elements of
        the signed object.</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[GET /resource/foo
Authorization: PoP eyJ....]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="HTTP Form body">
        <t>If the client is sending the request as a form-encoded HTTP message
        with parameters in the body, the client MAY send the signed object as
        part of that form body. The value of the signed object in JWS compact
        form is sent as the form parameter pop_access_token. Note that if this
        method is used, the body hash cannot be included in the protected
        elements of the signed object.</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[POST /resource
Content-type: application/www-form-encoded

pop_access_token=eyJ....]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="HTTP Query parameter">
        <t>If neither the Authorization header nor the form-encoded body
        parameter are available to the client, the client MAY send the signed
        object as a query parameter. The value of the signed object in JWS
        compact form is sent as the query parameter pop_access_token. Note
        that if this method is used, the pop_access_token parameter MUST NOT
        be included in the protected elements of the signed object.</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[GET /resource?pop_access_token=eyJ....]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Validating the request">
      <t>Just like with a <xref target="RFC6750">bearer token</xref>, while
      the access token value included in the signed object is opaque to the
      client, it MUST be understood by the protected resource in order to
      fulfill the request. Also like a bearer token, the protected resource
      traditionally has several methods at its disposal for understanding the
      access token. It can look up the token locally (such as in a database),
      it can parse a structured token (such as <xref
      target="RFC7519">JWT</xref>), or it can use a service to look up token
      information (such as <xref target="RFC7662">introspection</xref>).
      However token information is looked up, the protected resource MUST have
      access to the key associated with the access token, which is required to
      validate the signature of the incoming request. Validation of the
      signature is done using normal JWS validation for the signature and key
      type.</t>

      <t>Additionally, in order to trust any of the hashed components of the
      HTTP request, the protected resource MUST re-create and verify a hash
      for each component as described below. This process is a mirror of the
      process used to create the hashes in the first place, with a mind toward
      the fact that order may have changed and that elements may have been
      added or deleted. The protected resource MUST similarly compare the
      replicated values included in various JSON fields with the corresponding
      actual values from the request. Failure to do so will allow an attacker
      to modify the underlying request while at the same time having the
      application layer verify the signature correctly.</t>

      <section title="Validating the query parameter list and hash">
        <t>The client has at its disposal a map that indexes the query
        parameter names to the values given. The client creates a string
        buffer for calculating the hash. The client then iterates through the
        "list" portion of the "p" parameter. For each item in the list (in the
        order of the list) it does the following:</t>

        <t><list style="numbers">
            <t>Fetch the value of the parameter from the HTTP request query
            parameter map. If a parameter is found in the list of signed
            parameters but not in the map, the validation fails.</t>

            <t>Encode the parameter as "name=value" and concatenate it to the
            end of the string buffer, separated by an ampersand character.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>The client calculates the hash of the string buffer and base64url
        encodes it. The protected resource compares that string to the string
        passed in as the hash. If the two match, the hash validates, and all
        named parameters and their values are considered covered by the
        signature.</t>

        <t>There MAY be additional query parameters that are not listed in the
        list and are therefore not covered by the signature. The client MUST
        decide whether or not to accept a request with these uncovered
        parameters.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Validating the header list and hash">
        <t>The client has at its disposal a map that indexes the header names
        to the values given. The client creates a string buffer for
        calculating the hash. The client then iterates through the "list"
        portion of the "h" parameter. For each item in the list (in the order
        of the list) it does the following:</t>

        <t><list style="numbers">
            <t>Fetch the value of the header from the HTTP request header map.
            If a header is found in the list of signed parameters but not in
            the map, the validation fails.</t>

            <t>Encode the parameter as "name: value" and concatenate it to the
            end of the string buffer, separated by a newline character.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>The client calculates the hash of the string buffer and base64url
        encodes it. The protected resource compares that string to the string
        passed in as the hash. If the two match, the hash validates, and all
        named headers and their values are considered covered by the
        signature.</t>

        <t>There MAY be additional headers that are not listed in the list and
        are therefore not covered by the signature. The client MUST decide
        whether or not to accept a request with these uncovered headers.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <section title="The 'pop' OAuth Access Token Type">
        <t>Section 11.1 of <xref target="RFC6749"/> defines the OAuth Access
        Token Type Registry and this document adds another token type to this
        registry.</t>

        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Type name:">pop</t>

            <t
            hangText="Additional Token Endpoint Response Parameters:">(none)</t>

            <t hangText="HTTP Authentication Scheme(s):">Proof-of-possession
            access token for use with OAuth 2.0</t>

            <t hangText="Change controller:">IETF</t>

            <t hangText="Specification document(s):">[[ this document ]]</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="JSON Web Signature and Encryption Type Values Registration">
        <t>This specification registers the <spanx style="verb">pop</spanx>
        type value in the IANA JSON Web Signature and Encryption Type Values
        registry <xref target="RFC7515"/>: <list style="symbols">
            <t>"typ" Header Parameter Value: <spanx style="verb">pop</spanx></t>

            <t>Abbreviation for MIME Type: None</t>

            <t>Change Controller: IETF</t>

            <t>Specification Document(s): [[ this document ]]</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <section title="Offering Confidentiality Protection for Access to Protected       Resources">
        <t>This specification can be used with and without Transport Layer
        Security (TLS).</t>

        <t>Without TLS this protocol provides a mechanism for verifying the
        integrity of requests, it provides no confidentiality protection.
        Consequently, eavesdroppers will have full access to communication
        content and any further messages exchanged between the client and the
        resource server. This could be problematic when data is exchanged that
        requires care, such as personal data.</t>

        <t>When TLS is used then confidentiality of the transmission can be
        ensured between endpoints, including both the request and the
        response. The use of TLS in combination with the signed HTTP request
        mechanism is highly recommended to ensure the confidentiality of the
        data returned from the protected resource.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Plaintext Storage of Credentials">
        <t>The mechanism described in this document works in a similar way to
        many three-party authentication and key exchange mechanisms. In order
        to compute the signature over the HTTP request, the client must have
        access to a key bound to the access token in plaintext form. If an
        attacker were to gain access to these stored secrets at the client or
        (in case of symmetric keys) at the resource server they would be able
        to perform any action on behalf of any client just as if they had
        stolen a bearer token.</t>

        <t>It is therefore paramount to the security of the protocol that the
        private keys associated with the access tokens are protected from
        unauthorized access.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Entropy of Keys">
        <t>Unless TLS is used between the client and the resource server,
        eavesdroppers will have full access to requests sent by the client.
        They will thus be able to mount off-line brute-force attacks to
        attempt recovery of the session key or private key used to compute the
        keyed message digest or digital signature, respectively.</t>

        <t>This specification assumes that the key used herein has been
        distributed via other mechanisms, such as <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-oauth-pop-key-distribution"/>. Hence, it is the
        responsibility of the authorization server and or the client to be
        careful when generating fresh and unique keys with sufficient entropy
        to resist such attacks for at least the length of time that the
        session keys (and the access tokens) are valid.</t>

        <t>For example, if the key bound to the access token is valid for one
        day, authorization servers must ensure that it is not possible to
        mount a brute force attack that recovers that key in less than one
        day. Of course, servers are urged to err on the side of caution, and
        use the longest key length possible within reason.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Denial of Service">
        <t>This specification includes a number of features which may make
        resource exhaustion attacks against resource servers possible. For
        example, a resource server may need to process the incoming request,
        verify the access token, perform signature verification, and might (in
        certain circumstances) have to consult back-end databases or the
        authorization server before granting access to the protected resource.
        Many of these actions are shared with bearer tokens, but the
        additional cryptographic overhead of validating the signed request
        needs to be taken into consideration with deployment of this
        specification.</t>

        <t>An attacker may exploit this to perform a denial of service attack
        by sending a large number of invalid requests to the server. The
        computational overhead of verifying the keyed message digest alone is
        not likely sufficient to mount a denial of service attack. To help
        combat this, it is RECOMMENDED that the protected resource validate
        the access token (contained in the <spanx style="verb">at</spanx>
        member of the signed structure) before performing any cryptographic
        verification calculations.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Validating the integrity of HTTP Headers and Query Parameters">
        <t>This specification provides flexibility for selectively validating
        the integrity of header fields and message bodies. Since all
        components of the HTTP request are only optionally validated by this
        method, and even some components may be validated only in part (e.g.,
        some headers but not others) it is up to protected resource developers
        to verify that any vital parameters in a request are actually covered
        by the signature.</t>

        <t>The application verifying this signature MUST NOT assume that any
        particular parameter is appropriately covered by the signature unless
        it is included in the signed structure and the hash is verified. Any
        applications that are sensitive of header or query parameter order
        MUST verify the order of the parameters on their own. The application
        MUST also compare the values in the JSON container with the actual
        parameters received with the HTTP request (using a direct comparison
        or a hash calculation, as appropriate). Failure to make this
        comparison will render the signature mechanism useless for protecting
        these elements.</t>

        <t>The behavior of repeated query parameters or repeated HTTP headers
        is undefined by this specification. If a header or query parameter is
        repeated on either the outgoing request from the client or the
        incoming request to the protected resource, that query parameter or
        header name MUST NOT be covered by the hash and signature. [[ Note to
        the WG: is this something we need to cover? ]]</t>

        <t>This specification records the order in which query parameters and
        headers are hashed, but it does not guarantee that order is preserved
        between the client and protected resource.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Privacy Considerations">
      <t>This specification addresses machine to machine communications and
      raises no privacy considerations beyond existing OAuth transactions.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The authors thank the OAuth Working Group for input into this
      work.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7519"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7515"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7159"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7662"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6750"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6749"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-oauth-pop-key-distribution"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-oauth-pop-architecture"?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
